A Guide to the Papers of Gertrude Stein, 1907-1955, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Subseries A: Correspondence of Gertrude Stein
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir Francis Rose], n.d., ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:60)
      Arrived in the country where village life is "very absorbing and lengthy and amusing." They hope to be done with their proofs before Rose's preliminary visit. Stein is looking forward to his two new pictures.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir] Francis [Rose], n.d., ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:61)
      Critical response to one of Rose's paintings. Warns Rose that, although important for a painter to paint bad pictures, he should "beware of it becoming a habit." Tells him that he is no longer a young man and thus must decide his future.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir] Francis [Rose], n.d., ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:62)
      Likes the "St. Remy" painting "as much as ever and believes in Rose as a painter. She is sure he will find a solution to his "present and [his] future difficulties."
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir] Francis [Rose], n.d., ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:63)
      Wondering if everything is going well with Rose and still as interested in him as ever.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir] Francis [Rose], n.d., ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:64)
      Stein has found a buyer for one of his paintings, and mentions that she knows of someone who is painting in his manner: "it is not very beautiful but on the other hand not stupid." Hopes his dog is alright.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir] Francis [Rose], n.d., ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:65)
      Praises Roses two new pictures which are as fine as he has ever done. Describes in detail how his use of light in the paintings. She concludes by saying that she believes in him and would have "hated most awfully to give up that belief."
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir] Francis [Rose], n.d., ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:66)
      A dealer told Stein it is a good idea to introduce his work to the American public. She also wants to change galleries which would "undoubtedly be better" for Rose's future.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir] Francis [Rose], n.d., ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:67)
      Worried about Rose's dog, [Bayan], and wants him to dine with them on the 25th when he gets to Paris because they will be leaving on the 29th. Mentions how the cascade he did [at ?] "remains one of her favorite pictures." Stationary includes "A rose is a rose is a rose" embossing.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir] Francis [Rose], n.d., ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:68)
      Stein just returned from a trip and on coming back "had a great deal of pleasure out of quite a number" of his pictures. Sorry that he has not been well.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir] Francis [Rose], n.d., ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:69)
      Wants to know what is the matter with the post office where Rose lives because Abdy's letters have been returned and they intend on writing again. Stationary includes "A rose is a rose is a rose" embossing.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir] Francis [Rose], n.d., ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:70)
      Stein is pleased with Rose's pictures and discusses his development, in particular with the "milk-pail" still life. Hoped to see his show in Chicago but unfortunately will arrive too late to see it.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir] Francis [Rose], n.d., ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:71)
      Stein thanks Rose for the pictures.
    - Gertrude Stein to [William] Seabrook, n.d., ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:72)
      Stein just finished Seabrook's book and is "perfectly happy with every page." Stein is "so happy" in all he says of her, and is hoping he visits her soon.
    - Gertrude [Stein] to [William] Seabrook, n.d., ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:73)
      Stein mentions how she is happy to hear from Seabrook and that they have been wondering about him recently. She is happy to receive news and is very busy planting.
    - Gertrude [Stein] to Virgil [Thomson], n.d., ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l., with envelope. #8259. (Box-folder 1:74)
      Stein thanks Thompson for the marked copy with the changes he has made. Will send a presentation copy to him instead. Folder includes ALS, 1934 November 20, from [Van]. to Mr. Woolley which includes the background of the Stein letter, a transcription, and some anecdotes about Stein.
    - Gertrude Stein to [ ], n.d., APCS, 1 item. #8259. (Box-folder 1:75)
      Sorry that [the recipient] will not meet them, but hopefully later in Paris. Writes beneath her signature: "Born February 3 1874." Image on recto of postcard is of Stein with her dog, Basket.
  - Subseries B: Correspondence of Alice B. Toklas
    - A[lice] B. Toklas to M. H. Brown, 1931 April 16, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:76)
      Because of Axel's Castle, Toklas acknowledges that the work of Gertrude Stein is desired by the reading public. Consequently, it is a "favorable moment to secure orders for Lucy Church Amiable."
    - A[lice] B. Toklas to William Jackson, 1934 October 11, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:77)
      Writes that Stein did not write a book about Ernest Hemingway, but that he was "one of the writers she discusses" in The Autobiography of Alice B. Toklas.
    - A[lice] B. Toklas to Miss Lingafelt, 1934 December 1, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:78)
      Thanks Lingafelt for the "delicious white violets."
    - A[lice] B. Toklas to Bruce Humphries, Inc., 1935 June 4, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:79)
      Stein is incensed that she has to keep reminding them for the statement check, which to Stein is "an inexcusable negligence." Stein wants to make it clear that "for the present and the future" she expects her checks on time.
    - Alice [B.] Tolkas to [William S.] Byler, 1955 January 9, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l.; with envelope. #8259. (Box-folder 1:80)
      Wants to help out by contributing to the Yale Literary Magazine's number on Henri Matisse, but other than that his wife was very beautiful, there was not much more that she could contribute. But she will try to think of something soon.
- Series III: Miscellaneous Documents
  - Contract for Publication of Geography and Plays,1922 January 26, DS, 4 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 2:1)
    Initial contract with The Four Seas Company.
  - Contract for Publication of Geography and Plays, 1930, DS, 4 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 2:2)
    Transfer of copyright from The Four Seas Company to Bruce Humphries, Inc.
  - Envelope addressed to Miss Georgia Lingafelt, 1928 February 25, 1 item. #8259. (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Short biography of Gertrude Stein, n.d., Newsclipping. #8259. (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Scrapbook concerning Gertrude Stein, assembled by Edna Kenton, [ca. 1923-1935], 1 vol. #8259. (Box-folder 2:5)
    Includes: ALS, [Merle C.] Bartlett to Miss Kenton, 1929 July 5 re. a photograph of Stein; Photograph: "A Recent Study of Gertrude Stein" by Man Ray; Articles and clippings regarding Gertrude Stein; Various photographs of Stein; Articles regarding Sherwood Anderson; "The Philosopher" by Sherwood Anderson; "Vibrant Life" by Sherwood Anderson; "Sister" by Sherwood Anderson; "Sherwood Anderson" by Alyse Gregory.
- Series IV: Photographs
  - Portrait of Gertrude Stein by Pablo Picasso, [ca. 1920], 1 photograph. #8259. (Box-folder 2:6)
    Print used by Bruce Humphries, Inc.
  - Photograph of Gertrude Stein by Carl Van Vechten, 1935 February 4, 2 photographs. #8259-b, -d. (Box-folder 2:7)
    The photograph shows Stein on the Lawn in front of the Rotunda at the University of Virginia.
  - Photograph of Gertrude Stein, Alice B. Toklas, A.G.A. Balz, Scott Buchanan, Carl Van Vechten, Anna Barringer[?], and John Cook Wyllie on the Lawn at the University of Virginia, [ca. 1935 February 4], 1 photographic negative. (Box-folder 2:8)
    Includes one 8x10 enhanced photograph of negative. Gift of LeGrand Tennis of Phoebus.
  - Group photograph of Gertrude Stein, Alice B. Toklas, Emily Clark Balch, James Southall Wilson, and others, [ca. 1935 February 4], 1 photograph. #6453-f. (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Photograph of Gertrude Stein signing book, [ca. 1935], 1 photograph. #8259-a. (Box-folder 2:10)
  - Photograph of Jo Davidson sculpture of Gertrude Stein, n.d., 8 copies. (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Three newspaper photographs of Gertrude Stein, [ca. 1937-1946], #8259. (Box-folder 2:12)
  - Newspaper cut of Gertrude Stein, n.d., 1 item. #8259. (Box-folder 2:13)